<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<dictionary>
    <record>
        <word>Biên Hoà</word>
        <meaning>@Biên Hoà
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -Xem Đồng Nai
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Blowing dust and wind</word>
        <meaning>@Blowing dust and wind
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -(Gió bụi trên đường) The wind and dust blowing on the road
            -Troubled (times).
            =Thuở trời đất nổi cơn gió bụi+In troubled times by Heaven's will
            -Hard, full of ups and downs
            =Cuộc đời gió bụi+A life full of ups and downs
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Bình Định</word>
        <meaning>@Bình Định
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -Quy Nhơn, provincial capital of Bình Định, is 1,065km from Hà Nội on National Highway 1. In the old days,
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Bắc bán cầu</word>
        <meaning>@Bắc bán cầu
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -Northern hemisphere
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Bắc đẩu</word>
        <meaning>@Bắc đẩu
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -The Great Bear
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Chăm</word>
        <meaning>@Chăm
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -dân tộc Chăm
            -With about 100,000 inhabitants, Chăm (Chàm, Chiêm, Hời) ethnic group originates from Ancient Chăm Pa
            -THE UNIQUE CHĂM CULTURE: The Chăm culture is a unique tradition, contributing much to the+diversity and
            -The Chăm are one of the 53 ethnic groups in Vietnam and comprise various subgroups. There are around 98,000
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Dao</word>
        <meaning>@Dao
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -dân tộc Dao
            -With more than 400,000 inhabitants, Dao ethnic group occupies 0.65% of the
            =Vietnamese population and belongs to Mèo-Dao linguistic group. They live+at the altitude of 700-1000m,
            =considerable altitude. Most of them inhabit Hà Giang - Tuyên Quang, and+part of them in the northwest
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Giãn xương giãn cốt</word>
        <meaning>@Giãn xương giãn cốt
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -như giãn xương
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Hoà Bình</word>
        <meaning>@Hoà Bình
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -Located on Highway 6, Hoà Bình provincial capital is 70km southwest of Hà Nội. Hoà Bình town and the
        </meaning>
    </record>
    <record>
        <word>Hà Nội</word>
        <meaning>@Hà Nội
            *DEFAULT_TYPE
            -Hà Nội is the political capital of Vietnam. Hà Nội lies in Red River Delta and is situated in a tropical
            -Chùa một cột (One-pillar Pagoda): Its original name was Diên Hựu (long-lasting happiness and good luck).
            -Quốc Tử Giám (Temple of Literature) was built in 1070 as a dedication to the founder of Confucianism. Six
            -Chùa Kim Liên (Kim Lien Pagoda): Legend has it that in the 12th century, Princess Tu Hoa, daughter of King
            -Chùa Quán Sứ (Quan Su Pagoda) was built in the 17th century. It is located in the street of the same name.
            -Đền Quan Thánh (Quan Thanh Temple): The three ancient Chinese characters which are still seen today on the
            -Đền Hai Bà Trưng (Hai Bà Trưng Temple) is also called Đồng Nhân Temple, because it is located in Đồng Nhân
            -Hồ Tây (West Lake) &amp; Đường Thanh Niên (Youth Road): Youth Road can be compared to a beautiful bridge
            -Hồ Hoàn Kiếm (Lake of Restored Sword): The name of this lake is derived from a legend having it that a
            -Đền Ngọc Sơn (Ngoc Son Temple): Initially, the temple was called Ngọc Sơn Pagoda. Later, it was renamed as
            -NGHI TÀM: A VILLAGE OF FLOWERS? Once upon a time, the King of Nhà Hậu Lý decided to build a palace for
        </meaning>
    </record>
</dictionary>